Thomas McMaster BSc (Hons)

Data and Database Development.

Contact Information:

Email: <u>tommcmaster@protonmail.com</u>

LinkedIn: https://www.linkedin.com/in/thomasmcmastersql/

Online CV: https://thomas-mcmaster.github.io/

Personal Statement:

I am an IT professional who specializes in database development, administration and ETL. I have held data-related roles in the public, private and charitable sectors. In each of those posts I have produced high quality work that has improved processes, gained value from organizational data, and kept decision-makers informed.

My main skills are in SQL Server (2008 R2 to 2019), SSIS, and Microsoft PowerShell. I also have experience with Cloud products including Azure Data Factory and Synapse Analytics.

Personal Attributes:

- Efficient and well-organized.
- Comfortable working as part of a team or as an individual.
- Able to communicate detailed technical concepts clearly.
- Approachable with excellent face-to-face and written support skills.

Professional Qualifications:

- Microsoft Certified in Azure Fundamentals (AZ-900).
- Working towards PCEP certification with The Python Institute

Professional Experience:

March 2022 - present

Data Engineer - Hymans Robertson

Technologies: SQL Server 2008 R2 to 2019, PowerShell, SSIS, SSRS, Azure Dev Ops, Data Factory, Synapse Analytics, Kimball Data Warehousing Concepts, YAML

- Analysis and delivery of changes to pension scheme data via complex T-SQL scripting and stored procedures.
- Automated the transfer and anonymization of data between databases with PowerShell and YAML pipelines.
- Developed bespoke risk transfer reporting for in-house actuaries and external insurance firms.
- Data analysis to inform decision-makers involved in the UK government's Pensions Dashboard initiative.
- Introduced a reporting data warehouse moving on-premises data to Delta Lake with Synapse Analytics.
- Provisioned Cloud resources via CI and CD YAML-based pipelines and Bicep.
- Delivery of solutions and collaboration with colleagues via Git and Azure Dev Ops (ADO).

September 2020 -March 2022

Senior Data and Integration Officer - East Renfrewshire Council.

Technologies: SQL Server 2008 R2 to 2019, Oracle 12 to 19c, PowerShell, SSIS, SSRS, Git, RMAN.

- Council DBA with responsibility for the Authority's SQL Server and Oracle database estate.
- Automation of data transfers with scripted WinSCP.
- Delivery of new reporting suite to monitor health of the Council's database estate.
- Working with suppliers and third parties to ensure smooth data migrations to Cloud hosts.
- Introduction of nightly Oracle 'hot' backup solution to increase service availability.
- Creation of SQL Server corruption checker. Nightly check of 450 SQL databases for new DR strategy.
- Maintenance of Civica Icon and Servitor, NEC's Revenue's and Benefits, NEC Ohms, and Tribal's K2.
- Ongoing review of database security, roles, and the release of encryption-at-rest for SQL Server.

February 2019 – September 2020

Database Developer and BI Analyst - Maggie's.

Technologies: SQL Server (2008 R2 to 2017), thankQ CRM, SSIS, SSRS, VBA, Microsoft Office

- Automation of data pipelines (fundraising financials, stewardship communications, and event promotion).
- Creation of bespoke data extracts for fundraisers and campaign organisers.
- Monitoring and resolving database performance issues, backup strategy and scheduled maintenance.
- Requirements analysis with support staff, colleagues at 26 NHS hospitals, and senior stakeholders.
- Processing of requests sent to the Database Service Team's inbox.

June 2011 - February 2019

Systems Analyst / Programmer / Team DBA – Hymans Robertson

Technologies: SQL Server 2008 R2 to 2016, T-SQL, SSIS, MS Access, VBA, SSRS, Civica UPM2.

- KPI and SLA reporting to Management.
- Application support for the UPM2 pension management system and its underlying SQL Server databases.
- Troubleshooting and root cause analysis of Helpdesk System Support requests submitted by end users.
- Communication with stakeholders to identify issues, gather requirements and produce specifications.
- Lead analyst on projects for high profile clients.
- Business process and workflow analysis.
- Team DBA role to release production code, maintain SQL Server instances, and apply third-party product upgrades.

June 2010 – June 2011

Database Programmer (Contract) - Hewlett Packard

Technologies: SQL Server 2008 R2, SSRS, SSIS, VBA, Microsoft Office

- Working with the EMEA Software team to develop new sales reporting tools.
- Translating existing business processes for data automation.

March 2007 - June 2010

Asset and Systems Support Officer – East Ayrshire Council Roads and Transportation Service Technologies: SQL Server 2000 to 2008 R2, SSIS, Microsoft Office with VBA, Classic ASP.

- Service contact for all IT requests, troubleshooting and application support.
- Analysis and development of bespoke database applications for use by Roads Service staff.
- Administrator of GGP Gazetteer software.
- Maintenance of the authority's street gazetteer and associated data to BS7666 standard.
- Secretary of the Scottish Gazetteer Group.

June 2005 - March 2007

I.T. Technician - Booth Welsh Automation Ltd

Technologies: Microsoft Office with VBA.

- Responsible for IT system and application support across three sites.
- Working with end users across the business to assist with hardware and application issues.
- Development of relational database applications for all departments in the company.

June 2004 – June 2005

Systems Analyst (Contracting) - GlaxoSmithKline

Technologies: Microsoft Office with VBA, AspenTech process engineering tools.

Microsoft Excel and VBA development to interact with AspenTech process engineering software.

Education:

1999-2003:

Honours Degree (2:1) in Computer Studies from Glasgow Caledonian University.